Guide to the Herbert J. Gezork Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Class Lectures/Course Documentation, Series VI
  - Andover Newton Theological School
    - Cultural and Racial Conflicts
      - Lectures and other material, interfiled (Box 10)
        Strong, Organized anti-Semitism in America (2 pp. notes); H. Valentine, Antisemitism (quotation); Zionism A Program for Christian-Jewish understanding; Maritain, A Christian looks at the Jewish question (notes); Maritain, Ransoming the time (quotation); [Untitled, on practical solutions]; [Untitled; bibliography on white/black relations]; Bibliography [on blacks]; [Untitled, on roles of famous blacks]; Negro attitudes; Some statistics on Negro population; Who is a Negro?; The Negro-white problem; Ideological basis for exploitation and discrimination; Economic situation of Negro; Economic outlook for Negro in post war world; Legal discrimination [] Negro; Legislation on inter racial marriage; Interracial marriage; Protestantism and Negro in USA; What the churches do; What churches do! Locally; Main suggestions toward solution; Reviving an old idea (clipping, Christian Century, n.d.); Negro (2 pp. quotations); Protestant and Roman Catholic relations; Catholic-Protestant relations; Post Revolution period; Anti-Catholic movements; Recent period Prot.-R.C. tensions (pp. 1,3); R.C. attitude toward Protestants; What to do? Prot.-R.C. tensions (6 pp.); 17 [Untitled, on Catholics and presidential campaign] (pp. 8b, Be, quotation); Japanese Americans (3 folders); 70,000 American refugees [pamphlet] (Congregational Christian Committee for Work with Japanese Evacuees, n.d.); Some suggestions for the Christian minister or religious education leader; Springfield plan; Basic strategy (p. 1)
      - Clippings and pamphlets (Box 10)
        Tatsachen, mit denen wir rechnen mussen (no source, n.d.); What is the National Conference? (National Conference of Christians and Jews, n.d.); Christian sources of anti-Semitism: a symposium [offprint] (The Humanist, Autumn 1944); Beatrice Gross, Who speaks for the Jews? (Common Sense, Mar. 1944); John H. Marion, Welcome -- to all? (no source, n.d.); A primer on race (Council on Christian Social Progress, Northern Baptist Convention, 1945); Mrs. L. E. M. Freeman, Her name is Mary (no source; 1946?); Sam Jones, A Southern solution (Life, Mar. 14, 1949); [Untitled; quotation from John Pym on Catholicism, no source, n.d.]; Catholic laity forcing trend, says Oxnam (no source, n.d.)
    - Ethical Thought of Pre- and Non-Christian Civilizations
      - Lectures and other material, interfiled (Box 10)
        Description of the course; Termpapers; Examination, 1944/5; [Untitled; bibliography); Aspects of religious life; Literature: Primitive society; The Ethical thought in primitive society (2 folders); Babylonia-Assyria: Bibliography; Babylonia-Assyria (2 folders); Egypt [bibliography]; Egypt (2 folders); Zoroastrianism: Bibliography Zoroastrianism (2 folders); Islam: Bibliography; Islam (3 folders); India [bibliographic pamphlet] (Council on Books in War Time); [Untitled; bibliography]; India [bibliography]; Outline of Christian Ethics - 11, lst sem. 1938; (handwritten note: Reinh. Niebuhr); Outline; India; Literature; Hinduism (2 pp.); Hinduism (pp. 1-10c); [Untitled, on Hindu ethics]; Caste
      - Lectures and other material, interfiled (Box 11)
        Sex - marriage - family - woman; [Untitled; chart comparing western and eastern personality]; People of India; The Christian approach to Hinduism; Jainism; Buddhism: Bibliography; Buddhism (2 folders); Bibliography: China; A Chart of Confucian ethical concepts; History; China (3 folders); Shinto [bibliography]; Shinto (2 folders)
    - Social Ethics
      The following is material from courses taught at Andover Newton (1939/40-1950/51) and at Assumption College. As far as possible the material is arranged in the order of the syllabus "Christian Social Ethics: A brief outline of the course" (in Social Ethics -- Course Outlines file).
      - Course outlines (Box 11)
        Ecumenical Institute of Religious Studies, Assumption College [printed brochure]; Ecumenical Institute: Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications.; Christian Ethics Social Ethics I: A brief outline of the course; Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications. (2 versions); Christian Social Ethics. Christian Social Ethics: Christian Social Ethics. Christian Social Ethics. Economic relations. II. Applications, 2/62 A brief outline of the course I. Foundations II. Applications. B.; Christian living in today's world: a brief bibliography; Ten commandments on economic life for the minister
    - Social ethics -- Theological presuppositions
      - Mimeographed outlines, bibliographies, most with handwritten amendments: (Box 11)
        Christian Social Ethics: A brief outline of the course (2 versions); A. Presuppositions; Christian Social Ethics. I. Foundations.; Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications. A. Sex - Marriage - Family - Divorce; Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications. B.;Economic relations; Christian living in today's world: a brief bibliography; Christian Social Ethics (Ecumenical Institute, Assumption College) (2 versions); Bibliography for course in Christian Social Ethics, Ecumenical Institute of Religious Studies (2 versions); Bibliography for course in Christian Social Ethics; Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications; Ecumenical Institute: Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications. B. Economic relations. Ecumenical Institute: Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications. C. Political relations. Final examination, Ecumenical Institute, spring 1967/68 (2 versions)
      - Notes and correspondence (Box 11)
        Xn. soc(ial] ethics; [Untitled, on ethical decisions]; [Untitled; list of recommended books]; Books to read; [Untitled, on responses, decisions, issues]; [Untitled; introductory notes]; [Untitled, on faith and ethics; 2 pp.]; Letter dated Sept. 6, 1971, from HG to Max [Stackhouse]; reply on verso; Letter dated Dec. 26, 1967, from HG to Oscar [?]; enclosures: outline of course and reading list; Courses to offer
      - Lectures (Box 11)
        Introduction; Definition and classification of ethics (4 folders); Two misconceptions in Christian ethics; [Untitled, on individual and social ethics]; Rejection of purely individualistic Gospel; The Church; Decisions; The Nature of Christian decision (pp. 1-5); How does the Christian make his decision? (pp. 11-12); The Nature of Christian decision (pp. 1-9); The Problem of compromise; The Illusion of the reality of progress; The Christian, the church, and the world (pp.1-3, 6-10); [Untitled; quotation from Troeltsch on Thomism, marked p. 5]; Transition; The Protestant Reformation; Calvin; [Untitled, on Niebuhr's analysis of church/world relations] (pp. 1-3, marked as sections 4-5); Some roots of social wrongs (p. 6); [Untitled, on anthropocentric vs. theocentric religion]; War; Conflict; Non Violence and nonviolent resistance; Civil disobedience; Principles
      - Clippings (Box 11)
        Fletcher creates controversy (no date or source); Evangelicals confess an incomplete gospel (no date or source); Dr. Fletcher and the Ten Commandments (Tropic, 12/10/67); What price silence (Parade/Boston Globe, 2/11/68); Seminary professors spar on "situation ethics"([1970]); Problems and concepts which the church must face in its healing ministry (Grist, July 1973)
    - Social ethics -- Sex, marriage. family (Box 11)
      Fletcher creates controversy (no date or source); Evangelicals confess an incomplete gospel (no date or source); Dr. Fletcher and the Ten Commandments (Tropic,12/10/67); What price silence (Parade/Boston Globe, 2/11/68);Seminary professors spar on "situation ethics"([1970]); Problems and concepts which the church must face in its healing ministry (Grist, July 1973)
      - Mimeographed outlines, bibliographies (Box 11)
        Bible History. B. Specific problems. 1. Sex - Marriage - Family - Divorce (for course entitled Religion in Human Relationships, Pendle Hill Summer School, 1941); The Future of the family; Marriage and family in contemporary American life; I. Marriage and family in contemporary American life; II. The Family in Christian history
      - Questions: Suggestions for questions to be discussed; Questions out of reading (Box 11)
      - Lectures (Box 11)
        II. Applications. Sex - Marriage - Family - Divorce (7 folders); [Untitled; quotation from L.H. Thomas]; [Untitled; headed "last point"]; [Untitled, on Christianity in the Roman world; marked p. 3]; The Task of the Christian community (p. 1); [Untitled, on Jerome and Augustine]; [Untitled; Comte, Adler, and social order];Reformation (pp. Rl, R3); Sex - Marriage - Family - Divorce; Sex and marriage and family (marked (section] 5); What do about it?; [Untitled, on responsibility; marked p. 2];[Untitled, on the spiritual and physical]; Sex Christian approach; [Untitled, on Tertullian; marked pp. 2-4]; [Untitled; quotations from E.C. Gardner, Peter A. Bertocci]; [Untitled, on "Christian approach"]; [Untitled, on overemphasis of sex; marked p. 1a]
      - Lectures (Box 12)
        Sex and chastity; The Case for chastity and fidelity; [Untitled, on sex; pp. 3-4, 6-8, 10, 16]; Sex revolution; Sex; The Christian conception of sex; Kinsey report; Footnotes (pp. 3-5); [Untitled, on "where we go from here"]; [Untitled, on marriage; 1/2 p. handwritten); [Untitled, on marriage; 1/2 p. typed]; [Untitled, on divorce; 1/2 p.] [Untitled; quotation from Barry]; [Untitled; notes on Binkley, "What is right with marriage?"]; Marriages and divorces in the U.S.; Polygamy (Polygyny); Reasons for polygamy; Divorce (p. 4); Divorce (p. 4, section 5); [Untitled, on divorce; p. 2); [Untitled, on secularism and marriage; p. 8]; [Untitled; quotation from Tertullian; p. 1]; [Untitled; quotation from anonymous woman; p. 6]; [Untitled, on marriage; quotation from Brunner?]; Marriage and divorce; On R.C.;St. Paul; Christians and Jews; Religion and broken homes; Endogamy/exogamy; Mixed marriages; Mixed marriages R.C.; Gordis, Sex and the family; Vatican Council II; Zimmerman and Cervantes, "Successful American families"; [Untitled, on Jewish and Catholic divorces]; The Family in Christian history; Christian guideposts for responsible parenthood; Religious groups - birth control; Summing up; The Future of the family
      - Student lecture: Sex and family (lecture by R.N.) (Box 12)
      - Clippings (Box 12)
        Morals on the campus (Newsweek, n.d.); Joe E. Trull, A Moral counterattack (no source, n.d.); Howard Whitman, Science takes a new look at sex in America (This Week, Oct. 25, 1959); Charles B. Ketcham, The Search for the new morality; (Christian Century, Oct. 12, 1966); Waverley Root, Sex and the double standard (American Mercury, Oct. 1947); Margaret Culkin Banning, The Case for chastity (Reader's Digest, Aug. 1937); Seward Hiltner, Is Kinsey's view anti-Christian?(Christian Century, Oct. 28, 1953); Chad Walsh, Marriage and Christianity (Christian Century, Nov. 2, 1949); Denis de Rougemont, The Romantic route to divorce (The Observer [Brown University], n.d.); Law ponders case of 10-year bride; 12-year child bride pleads for husband (no source; 1938); Benjamin Lotz, An Un-American marriage (Christian Century, 1944); Un-American marriages [letters] (Christian Century,Nov. 1944); Mixed marriages and the Council (The Ecumenist, Dec. 1962); Rev. W.E.R. O'Gorman, Mixed marriages: marriages between Protestants and Roman Catholics [pamphlet] (privately printed, 1961); Mixed marriages (Inf. Service, June 22, 1946); Leland Foster Wood, If I marry a Roman Catholic (pamphlet] (National Council of Churches, 1945); Rabbi Roland B. Gittelsohn, Reform rabbis and mixed marriage [sermon] (Temple Israel of Boston, Jan. 13, 1961); Murray H. Leiffer, Mixed marriages and church loyalties (Christian Century, Jan. 19, 1949); Murray H. Leiffer, Mixed marriages and the children (Christian Century, Jan. 26, 1949); Shall I marry a Catholic? (Young People's Leader? 1948?); Progress forward: Algerian males lose "I divorce you" rights (no source, no date); Wayne Hanley, Divorce rate mountainous (Boston Sunday Herald, Jan. 16, 1970); Statement on responsible parenthood (Interchurch News, March 1961); "The Last socially acceptable form of bigotry" [pamphlet] (Legal Foundation for Personal Liberties, n.d.); To preserve freedom... [pamphlet] (Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, n.d.); The Christian Living Will
    - Social ethics -- Economic relations
      - Mimeographed assignments and questions (Box 12)
        Christian Social Ethics. II. Applications. B.; Economic relations.; Ecumenical Institute. Christian Social Ethics. II.; Applications. B. Economic relations.; Ten commandments on economic life for the minister; Ten commandments on economic life for the Christian minister; On economic problems; On work, wages, wealth, stewardship
      - Lectures (Box 12)
        Introduction to: economic relations, political relationship; O.T.; Economics: Jesus; Christianity, Jesus; Early Christianity; Medieval Christianity; Discrepancy between theory and practice; The Protestant Reformation and economic relations; The Puritans; Just price; Work; Work; Eco[nomic] life; "What is Christian vocation?"; "God and the daily life"; [Untitled, on ultimate truth]; Leisure; How to make work a creative experience?; Rewards of work; [Untitled, on work]; Jesus on possessions; Possessions. Property; Property; [Untitled, on property; 1/2 p.];[Untitled, on Jewish and Christian views of property]; [Untitled, on economic systems]; [Untitled, on profit; pp. 7-8); The Rise of capitalism; What is capitalism?; Capitalism; Pro capitalism; Contra capitalism; A Christian critique of capitalism, socialism, communism; [Untitled, on capitalism; 3 pp. marked "Ee."]; [Untitled; chart comparing Adam Smith and Karl Marx]; Marxian communism; Marxism; How in action?
      - Lectures (Box 12)
        Behind the Iron Curtain; Communism; Christianity and Communism; The Communism of the early church (1 p. summary); The Communism of the early church (lecture); Marxism; A Christian critique of M[arxist] Com[munism] (pp. 7-10); [Untitled, on Christian view of economics; pp. 8-10]; Criticism of M[arxist] Com[munism]; [Untitled; "true & right" vs. "false and wrong"]; Communism; [Untitled; chart of dialectics]; Stephen T. Possony [notes from lecture?]; Economic problems; Economics: basic considerations for Christians; Economic relations; [Untitled; notes on Christian economics]; [Untitled, on stewardship; pp. 6-8]; [Untitled; notes on production]; Religion and economic life; Development of economic systems; Economic systems; [Untitled, on American economics]; [Untitled, on work]; Christianity and economic systems; [Untitled, on religion and economic systems]; [Untitled, on personal stance]; [Untitled, on choice; p. 2]; [Untitled, on compromise; lecture notes?]; [Untitled, on church and economics; pp. 4-6]; The Chrisrian church in the economic crisis; Social change; The Struggle for economic justice; Points of conflict [between Christianity and Marxism]
      - Quotations, by source (Box 12)
        Gezork, So sah ich die Welt; Paul Ne---?; Niebuhr, Reinhold, Doom and dawn; Raven, C.E., Christian Socialism; Adam Smith, The Wealth of nations; [anon.] "Easy lessons on money matters ... "; Wilberforce, An inquiry into the state of mind amongst the laborers; Wilberforce, Practical view of the system of Christianity
      - Clippings (Box 12)
        Family incomes (graphs); Division of buying power in 1929 (graph)
    - Social ethics -- Politics, war
      - Mimeographed outlines, bibliographies (Box 12)
        Ecumenical Institute. Christian Social Ethics. II.; Applications (mimeographed outline); Christian Social Ethics. II. C. Political relations(mimeographed bibliography with notes added); Examination in course: Christian Social Ethics, Kanto Gakuin University
      - Lectures (Box 12)
        Political problems; [Untitled; charts of Niebuhr's models of church/world relations] (3 versions); [Untitled; outline of Niebuhr's models]; Basic observations; Attitudes to government (chart; 2 versions); [Untitled, on attitudes to government]; Christianity and the state; Jesus on state; [Untitled; quotations from Luther on temporal and spiritual humanity]; [Untitled, on Calvin and state]; Development since Reformation; "Befehlnotstand"; Religion and political relations; The Christian in politics (1 p.); The Christian in politics (pp. 1-[4]); The Christian and politics; The Christian in politics (pp. 1-3, 5-6); Aims & goals for foreign policy; Religion & war; Christian attitudes toward war; The Just war; Christianity and war; War (pp. 7-10); War ( 1 p. ); War {pp. 1-2); B. War. A divided attitude (6 pp.); War in Christian history; Luther; Calvin; Cromwell; Anabaptists; Erasmus; Statement in last war [Quakers]; War (12 pp.)
      - Lectures (Box 13)
        War (pp. 5-6); The Christian and war (pp. 7-8); [Untitled, on war and Christian ethics]; In time of war; War and peace; The New situation; Christian conscience and atomic war; Christian faith and atomic war; Christian conscience and atomic war (Peace, war, and pacifism); [Letter in response to lecture by Gezork, from Charlotte S. Bailey, March 26, 1941]; [Letter from Gezork to Charlotte Bailey, undated]; Religious p[acifis]m; Bases of Christian pacifism; Pacifism ( 1 p.); Pacifism (6 pp.); Non-Pacifism vs. Pacifism; Must Christians be pacifists?;[Untitled, on pacifism]; The Basis of Quaker peace testimony; Quaker education, XI (Pendle Hill Summer School); What has the Church to say? (pp. 18-21); Peace with justice
      - Clippings (Box 13)
        Brand Blanshard, May a non-pacifist be a Quaker? (sic)[excerpt] (The American Friend, July 17, 1941); This the Quaker believes: the Pennsylvania experiment (no source, n.d.); Edward B. Fiske, War and the clergy (New York Times, Feb. 15, 1966); John Cogley, Immediate peace urged by leaders of church council (New York Times, Feb. 17, 1966); The Text of church leaders' statement on Vietnam (New York Times, Feb. 17, 1966); [Circular letter] (Metropolitan Boston Affiliate, National Emergency Committee of Clergy Concerned about Vietnam, March 3, 1966); Robert Zevin, Background information on U.S. intervention in the Dominican Republic (Massachusetts, Political Action for Peace, n.d.); Guided missiles (Destiny, Apr. 1955); Kalter Krieg: Am Wendepunkt (Der Spiegel, Nr. 31, 1963); Der 1250 fache Tod (Der Spiegel, Nr. 31, 1963); Lewis Mumford, The Morals of extermination [pamphlet]; (American Friends Service Committee, reprinted from Atlantic Monthly, Oct. 1959); Norman K. Gottwald, A Sleep of prisoners (Worldview, Nov. 1964); What Civil Defense doesn't tell you (Greater Boston Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy, n.d.); Draft leaflet (Act for Peace, n.d.); What would be the destruction from a nuclear war? (no source, n. d.); H-bomb "hits" -- 40 cities (National Affairs, July 6, 1959); "Between a risk and a certainty a sane man does not hesitate" [pamphlet] (SANE, n.d.) Ronald Steel, The Cost of survival [offprint] (SANE, reprinted from Commonweal, Oct. 13, 1961); Widening perimeter of fiery death (Missions, Apr. 1955); Seek U.N. supervision of atomic tests (Christian Century, Mar. 16, 1955); French scientist says H-bomb danger point reached (Christian century, Dec. 1954); Man walks toward the shadows (Christian Century, Nov. 24, 1954); For UN: 56 cents a year (Christian Century [1955?]); How bad it is ... what we can do about it now (Newsweek, Apr. 6, 1959); How much Strontium 90? (no source, n.d.); Broadening aspects of the radiation peril (Christian Century, Feb. 1955); Radioactivity, food, and you [pamphlet] (no source, n.d.)
    - World Mission of the Christian Church
      (course taught 1945/46-1953/54)
      - Outlines and bibliographies (Box 13)
        Huston Smith, Christianity and other religions (notes); Books recommended for G.I.s; Questionnaires; My own interest in missions; Book suggestions by H. Cornell Goerner (clipping)
      - Exams and quizzes (Box 13)
      - Lectures (Box 13)
        Including: A Brief survey of world Christianity; The Missionary motive; Why must the Christian church be missionary?; Missionary education and emphasis in the church; [Untitled, on need for missions]; The Scriptural basis for missions; New Testament (marked section B); The Theological motivation of Christian missions; Brief survey of history of Christian world missions (4 folders); Ev[angelism] and missions (Ferre; notes?); Colonial organization = Mission organization (chart); Mass conversion vs. individual conversion; The Methods of Christian missions
      - Clippings (Box 13)
  - Brown University
    - Religion and Society
      (course taught spring 1966; interfiled is material for course titled Sociology of Religion, place and date unknown)
      - Outlines, bibliographies, course documentation (Box 13)
      - Exams (Box 13)
      - Lectures (Box 13)
        Emile Durkheim, The Elementary forms of the religious life (2 folders); Religion; Sociology: Main problems; Main types of rel[igion]; Lloyd Warner, The Family of God; Conservative Judaism; Carlin-Mendlowitz, The American Rabbi; Herberg, Protestant-Catholic-Jew; Fichter, A Typology of parishioners; Robert W. Spike, The Freedom revolution and the churches; Sociology of religion (marked "Lecture, Keuka College"); Soc[iology] of rel[igion] (questions for students); Sociology of religion (introduction and outline); Sociology of religion (lecture, 3 folders); [Untitled, on religion and various social structures]; The Sociological significance of religious experience and expression
      - Lectures (Box 14)
        The Religion of natural communities (2 folders); "The World" in the light of religious experience; Relations of religions to each other; Absorption and merger; Types of religious personality; Summing up
  - Furman University
    - Psychology of Religion
      (course taught 2nd semester 1937/38)
      - Reading assignments (Box 14)
      - Psych[ology] of Rel[igion] final exam (Box 14)
      - Lectures (Box 14)
        Psychology of religion (pp. 1-6 and 5 unnumbered pages); Psychology of religion (3 pp.); The Religion of childhood; The Religion of adolescence; Conversion; Revivals; Extreme religious emotionalism; Spiritism (includes clipping: Louis Adamic, The Millvale Apparition; Reader's Digest? 1938?); Belief in God; Belief in immortality; Cult and worship; Objective and subjective worship (includes clipping: Why they don't attend church; no source, n.d.); Prayer-questionnaire; [Untitled; tabulation of answers to questionnaire]; [Untitled; response to questionnaire]; Prayer; Mysticism; The New psychology and religion
      - Clippings (Box 14)
  - Harvard Divinity School
    - Preaching
      (course taught 1965/66)
      - Lectures and other material (Box 14)
      - Clippings (Box 14)
  - Wellesley College
    - Old Testament course
      Biblical History material was most likely also used for courses taught at Furman University.
      - Quizzes and exams, 1940–1943 (Box 14)
      - Lectures (Box 14)
      - Materials filed in order given in the "Brief outline of Hebrew history" in the Old Testament Introduction file (Box 14)
      - Materials filed in order given in the "Brief outline of Hebrew history" in the Old Testament Introduction file (Box 15)
    - New Testament course - Jesus
      - Lectures and other material (Box 15)
      - Lectures and other material (Box 16)
  - Course location not indicated
    - Church History lectures (Box 16)
- Student Papers, Series VII
  - Lecture notes--Winter-Semester, 1927–1928 (Box 16)
  - Prof. Wolf von Harnack, Die Entstehung des N.T (Box 16)
  - Prof. Julius Richter, Die indische Religionen (Box 16)
  - Ph.D.dissertation: The philosophical and ethical conceptions of Marxian Socialism (Box 16)